hi I'm Steven with Ledger gurus and in
this video I'm going to talk about
contribution margin we will unpack
everything you need to know to
understand calculate and use
contribution margin to optimize your
profitability let's start with the
basics of contribution margin every sale
you make brings in Revenue but not all
that money stays in your pocket to
understand how much of that actually
contributes to your operations and your
profit let's dive into variable and
fixed costs variable costs increase as
your sales increase fixed costs on the
other hand stay constant regardless of
how much you sell in the world of
e-commerce variable costs include things
like cost of goods sold fulfillment and
shipping costs payment processor fees
and advertising costs these costs can be
categorized as cost of goods sold or
cost of sales or total cost of sales
fixed costs would include things like
payroll software rent non-advertising
marketing spend and so on in theory
variable costs go up proportionately
with sales and fixed costs stay constant
in reality the variable costs vary and
fixed costs do have to go up as your
business gets bigger for example you'll
see different product costs by skew or
product item shipping costs can vary
based on the product item size weight or
bundle of products Payment Processing
fees can vary based on the credit card
that the customer uses finally
advertising costs can vary by the month
week day and even time of day fixed
costs can't stay fixed forever as your
business grows eventually you're going
to have to increase those costs they
typically increase in Step functions
calculating your contribution margin is
straightforward you simply subtract your
variable costs from your Revenue what
you're left over over withth is used to
pay your fixed costs and ultimately
generate a profit you can calculate
contribution margin at the product item
level at the sales Channel level and
ultimately at the overall business level
Let's do an example at the product item
level say that you're selling a product
for $20 and the variable costs are $14
you're left with $6 in contribution
margin if you wanted to calculate a
contribution margin ratio you divide the
$6 of contribution margin by the $20 of
Revenue and that would give you a 30%
contribution margin rate ratio there are
a few key insights to take away from
contribution margin first your
profitability will never exceed your
contribution margin if your contribution
margin is 30% your net operating income
ratio or operating margin ratio is never
going to be greater than that second
takeaway if you have a contribution
margin of 0% or less you have a broken
business your fundamental pricing and
variable costs must change you need to
raise prices and or decrease your cost
of goods and or decrease your cost of
sales act quickly if you find yourself
in this situation third take way is you
can use your contribution margin ratio
and your fixed cost to determine a break
even Revenue point for example if you
had a contribution margin of 30% and
fixed cost of $300,000 to determine your
break even Revenue you would simply
divide your fixed cost of $300,000 by
your 30% contribution margin which gives
you a million do at a million dollar in
sales you're Break Even anything above
that should generate profit as I
mentioned earlier reality is a bit
Messier but this calculation will get
you to the right target finally there is
great benefit at tracking the the
contribution margin at the business
level there is also benefit at tracking
the contribution margin at the sales
Channel level this will allow you to
determine if selling through Amazon or
Shopify is generating the margins that
you expect tracking contribution margin
at the product item or skew level can
also be beneficial but very timec
consuming start at the top work your way
down calculating contribution margin
requires good accounting and in
particular acral accounting there are
some additional videos in the comments
that will help you with a lot of the
concepts that I've discussed if you want
to go deeper on any of them if you need
need help determining your contribution
margin help with your e-commerce
accounting or just help with business
advisory reach out to us in the link in
the comments and if you found this video
helpful like it ask me a question in the
comments and subscribe to our channel
for more content like this